<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The vvidovves ioy. Or Christ his comfortable saluation to a comfortlesse widow being obseruations no lesse profitable then comfortable for the losse of our deceased friends. By W.C.</title>
            <author>Cragge, William, 1595 or 6-1636.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17510</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4323</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114181</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849409</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849409</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14554</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17510)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14554)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1266:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The vvidovves ioy. Or Christ his comfortable saluation to a comfortlesse widow being obseruations no lesse profitable then comfortable for the losse of our deceased friends. By W.C.</title>
                  <author>Cragge, William, 1595 or 6-1636.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 49, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by J. Bill] for Iohn Hodgets,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>W.C. = William Cragge.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Consolation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14554:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14554:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE WIDOWES IOY. <hi>OR</hi> CHRIST his comfortable SALVTATION <hi>To a comfortleſſe Widow:</hi> Being Obſeruations no leſſe profitable then comfortable for the loſſe of our <hi>deceaſed friends.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>W. C.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for IOHN HODGETS.</p>
            <p>1622.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:14554:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14554:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>LVKE 7. verſ. 13.</bibl>
               <q>When the Lord ſaw her, he had compaſsion on her, and ſayd vnto her, Weepe not.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> tels vs, that <hi>heauineſſe may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure for a night, but ioy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth in the morning:</hi> and our Sauiour himſelfe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth a bleſſedneſſe to them that <hi>mourne, for they ſhall be comforted:</hi> which comfortable doctrine hee hauing imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly in the Chapter going before deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered in words, he doth now here by his deedes, make good on the behalfe of a poore Widow miſerably mourning, and lamenting for the loſſe of the ſtaffe and comfort of her life; her ſonne, her onely ſonne, now vpon the Biere, carying to the place of buriall: Whom when the Lord ſaw, <hi>he had compaſsion on, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:14554:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Lord]</hi> This ſhewes vnto vs his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer: <hi>[ſaw her]</hi> here is his prouidence: <hi>[had compaſsion]</hi> here is his mercy, power, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, and mercy, meete all together to comfort this comfortleſſe Widow, <hi>Weepe not.</hi> His power was ſeene in raiſing her dead ſonne: his prouidence, in that hee ſaw her: his mercy, in commiſerating her griefe; her griefe, and the death of her ſonne, worke both together for her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort: for <hi>the Lord ſeeing her, hath compaſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on her:</hi> And thus are we brought into the Text.</p>
            <p>Which I may fitly terme a Comedy; it begins with ſorrow, and ends with ioy: acted by two perſons, which I make the two parts of my Text: <hi rend="sup">1</hi> a miſerable wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>[her]</hi> 
               <hi rend="sup">2</hi> a mercifull comforter, <hi>[The Lord.]</hi> The woman is a Widow, the comforter is Chriſt: The woman acting a mournfull Tragedie, Chriſt making it end with a ioyfull <hi>Plaudite:</hi> In the one there is great miſery, in the other, end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and boundleſſe mercy: Great miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie; for here is a voyce heard of mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:14554:3"/> weeping, and great lamentation; a Widow weeping for her onely ſonne, and could not be comforted, becauſe he was not: greater mercy; for Chriſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> puts on the bowels of <hi>compaſsion,</hi> and without any intreaty, reſtores miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly life to her ſonne, and vnexpectedly comfort to her ſelfe. Firſt, of <hi>her,</hi> the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and her miſery.</p>
            <p>Touching the hiſtorie, it ſtandeth thus: Chriſt hauing finiſhed his Sermon in the Mount, he came downe vnto the citie of <hi>Capernaum,</hi> where hee healed the Centurions ſicke ſeruant, and the next day he went vnto <hi>Naim,</hi> of which city this woman was an inhabitant: as he was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into this citie, there met him a great multitude, carrying a Coarſe, and this woman the mother, attending it with weeping eyes, whoſe miſery, and cauſe of ſorrow will appeare to be iuſt and great, if we doe weigh theſe ſubſequent paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.</p>
            <p>Firſt this <hi>[her:]</hi> this woman was not of the meaneſt or inferiour ſort of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14554:4"/> of the Citie, whoſe daily wants and neceſſities ſo inures and accuſtomes them with patience to beare many croſſes and miſeries, inſomuch that vnto them they ſeeme leſſe burdenſome: for <hi>mali conſuetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem mali amaritudinem adimit.</hi> And as they that are alwaies accuſtomed to liue in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh and fennie places, are not ſo much offended with noyſome foggie ſmels, as are they that liue in a more delicate and pure tract of ayre: So they whom their meaneneſſe of eſtate and condition, muſt many times make to want, yea in their greateſt aboundance to be full of wants, goe more lightly away with the burdens of miſerie and misfortune, then ſuch as haue theſe outward bleſſings of the world in greater aboundance. This wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man (I ſay) was not like in any probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie to haue beene of the meaner and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour ranke; for then ſhee might haue beene better able to haue paſſed this ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, as neceſſitie had made <hi>her</hi> ſubiect to many a former: but ſhee was of good e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme and account in the Citie, which
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14554:4"/> may bee gathered by this circumſtance, that ſhe went not alone, or with ſome few vnto the graue, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a great troupe and multitude, which we know is either out of honour and loue to the deceaſed, or out of reſpect vnto the liuing: it could not bee altogether out of honour and reſpect to the dead, for hee was but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a very young man, and not as yet of any deſert in the Citie, and therefore we may more then probably coniecture, that it was done as an honour vnto this VVidow, the mother of this young man, being ſome honorable and wel-reſpected Matron; yet this woman ſhee loſeth <hi>her</hi> ſonne, ſhe feeleth the ſmart of miſery.</p>
            <p>To teach vs this leſſon: That there is no ſexe, no age, no eſtate or condition whatſoeuer, which is, or can bee exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from ſorrow and miſerie: not onely the poore begger that hath but from hand to mouth, but euen the greateſt Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentate or Prince that euer liued, muſt haue his cares and cauſes of griefe. Croſſes and afflictions are not tyed or limited to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:14554:5"/> any climate or countrey, to any family or kindred: age cannot priuiledge a man, wiſedome cannot protect, policie cannot preuent, riches cannot purchaſe immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, but as God cauſeth the Sunne to ſhine ouer all the world, on the vniuſt, as well as on the iuſt: ſo doth he ſend croſſes, and cauſes of vexation and ſorrow, as well to the honourable and rich, as to the poore and ignoble. Wee will looke no farther then to <hi>Salomons</hi> cenſure of this: <hi>I ſought in my heart to enioy whatſoeuer was had by any of the ſonnes of men; I haue made me great houſes, &amp;c. and whatſoeuer mine eyes deſired, I with-held it not from them. Then I looked on all the workes that my hands had wrought, and on all the trauell I had laboured to doe, and behold, all is vanity and vexation of ſpirit.</hi> All thoſe his delights and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, riches and treaſures, could not giue him ſo much content, as to counteruaile the ſorrow, anxiety, and vexation of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit which he was continually ſubiect vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. And therefore Lawyers define life by weeping. The crying of children is a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14554:5"/> lawfull proofe of their liuing, to poſſeſſe the miſeries of this world: and at our go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out God is ſaid to wipe off teares, that is, to take away labour and ſorrow to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
            <p>Whereby is iuſtly reprooued the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull ſottiſhneſſe of worldly men, that dote ſo much vpon the momentary and ſinfull pleaſures of this ſinfull world, and looke for no other content, then what they make vnto themſelues in the enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of worldly things: Oh ſhow won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully haue men their hearts glued to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſmall contentment they finde heere, and thinke if they haue gotten much goods, and ſtore of treaſure, and haue laded themſelues with honour and digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that then they are out of the reach of croſſes. No, let no man thinke theſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things to be any better then <hi>Adams</hi> figge leaues, to hide our nakedneſſe, and to ſhelter vs from thoſe croſſes, which are incident vnto vs. Let no man put their truſt in theſe, for they will prooue <hi>like vnto a Reede, on which if a man leane, it</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:14554:6"/> 
               <hi>will runne into his hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, as this woman was wealthy and of good eſteeme, ſo ſhee was a wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow; ſhee had beene before a married woman, and as ſhee had participated of thoſe bleſſings which attend VVedlocke, ſo ſhee had many times felt thoſe cares, which are incident vnto thoſe who haue the care and charge of a Family; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made a mother, felt no doubt the trueth of Gods ſentence, I will greatly encreaſe thy ſorrow, in ſorrow ſhalt thou bring foorth thy children; and yet to adde more vnto <hi>her</hi> griefe, and which may ſeeme the greateſt griefe of all, <hi>her</hi> huſband, one halfe of <hi>her</hi> ſelfe dyes; and that not in his old and decrepit age, when all his pleaſure was gone, and life it ſelfe growne to be but labour and ſorrow: but in the flower of his youth, and not long after his mariage, which probably may be gathered by this, that hee left but one onely ſonne, and this our Sauiour calles <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a yong Stripling, all which muſt needs make <hi>her</hi> widow-hood the more
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14554:6"/> grieuous (widow-hood in it ſelfe beeing a croſſe great enough) inſomuch that the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> reckoneth, and puts it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his Imprecations and curſes on Gods and his enemies. <hi>Let his children bee</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 109.</note> 
               <hi>fatherleſſe, and his wife a Widow.</hi> So the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Ieremie, Lam.</hi> 1. 1. Lamenting and bewailing, the miſerable eſtate of <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> ſpeaketh thus; <hi>How doth the citie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine ſolitary that was full of people.</hi> Shee is as a widow: And Chapter 5. 5. <hi>Wee are fatherleſse without fathers, and our mothers are Widowes:</hi> yet all this while ſhe beares theſe croſſes manfully, ſhe yeelds not vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhee breakes not into open weeping, but comforts her ſelfe, calling to minde thoſe many and ſweet promiſes, and comforts made by God vnto VVidowes: for God hath promiſed to defend the fatherleſſe and widowes. <hi>The Lord your God is God of gods, which doth right vnto the fatherleſſe an Widowes.</hi> And <hi>Pſalme 146. 9. The Lord kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth the Stranger, he releeueth the fatherles and Widowes;</hi> Yea, the Lord commits the care of them vnto Magiſtrates, charging them
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14554:7"/> and all others, <hi>Ex. 22. 22. You ſhall not trouble the widow nor the fatherleſse childe:</hi> yea, the Lord out of his loue and care towards them, appoints part of the Tythe, for their reliefe. <hi>Deut.</hi> 14. 29. Hee would haue them to bee remembred in their Feaſtes; Hee menaceth a curſe againſt him that <note place="margin">Deut. 27. 29.</note> wrongeth the widow: <hi>Curſed be hee that hindreth the cauſe of the ſtranger, the father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, and VVidow.</hi> And <hi>Ieremie</hi> 5. 25. hee reckoneth the neglecting of the widow, one cauſe of the deſtruction of the people.</p>
            <p>VVith theſe and many other promiſes which ſhee found in Scripture no doubt but ſhee did continually comfort <hi>her</hi> ſelfe in <hi>her</hi> widow-hood, that though ſhee were yong, yet ſhe did not affect a ſecond marriage, and beſides ſhee tooke it as a pledge of Gods great fauour vnto <hi>her,</hi> that hee had giuen her a ſonne to bee a ſtay, and a comfort vnto <hi>her</hi> in <hi>her</hi> widow-hood: But ſee, to adde yet more vnto the complement of <hi>her</hi> miſerie; God, who knowes how to <hi>giue vs tearesto drinke in meaſure,</hi> and knoweth beſt when he hath
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14554:7"/> laid ſorrow &amp; affliction enough vpon his children, leaues not the widow thus. As not ſhee, ſo neither are wee worthy to know whereunto wee are reſerued. This <hi>her</hi> yong ſonne dyes, who was the light of <hi>her</hi> eyes, and the ioy of <hi>her</hi> life. To ſhew vnto vs thus much by the way; that not onely old men muſt, but the yongeſt that is may die, wee are no ſooner come into the world, but wee haſten out of the world: The pace of death is ſoft and ſure, and euery man is a dying man till he be dead. And therefore, wee muſt ſo ſet our mortality before our eyes, as to thinke euery day our laſt day, and labour care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to <hi>redeeme the time</hi> ill paſt, becauſe ſo vncertaine is the time of our abode.</p>
            <p>But what had this yong man done, thus vntimely to bee cropt off in the budde of his yeeres? Hee was but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a very yong man, as his tender yeeres could not patronize good counſell, and want of grauitie giue authoritie to his perſon, to be a preſident of vertue, ſo it is likely he was not yet miſled by the errors of youth,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14554:8"/> much leſſe could hee haue beene a ring-leader vnto euill. Or why ſhould we lay ſinne to his charge, when the holy Ghoſt layes none; but rather charitably, yea con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently perſwade our ſelues, that hee that was now about to doe ſo much for his body, had before done much more for his ſoule. Happily, God tooke him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, that hee ſhould not ſee the euill to come. And truely, if the mother had right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſidered this, it had beene a cauſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to mitigate, then any way to exaſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate or aggrauate <hi>her</hi> griefe, that God had ſo timely thus well prouided for her ſon; that though ſhe had loſt a ſonne, yet hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen had found a Saint, and though hee had beene neuer ſo deare and precious in her eyes, yet to haue reioyced, that ſhee had <hi>layd vp her treaſure in heauen.</hi> Had hee beene an vnnaturall <hi>Cain,</hi> a prophane <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau,</hi> a proud aſpiring <hi>Abſolon,</hi> an vſurping <hi>Adonijah;</hi> this might haue redoubled <hi>her</hi> griefe, to conſider, that from <hi>her</hi> loynes a chip ſhould haue beene hewen, to make a fire-brand in hell. But to haue a godly
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14554:8"/> yong <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> to be taken away in his ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der yeeres, that he might not ſee the euill to come; might cauſe <hi>her</hi> rather to mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie his mercie, then to whine vnder the rod of correction. And heereof ſhould all parents make a comfortable vſe, when at any time God ſhall deale with them in the like caſe, by remoouing their hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full yong plants, from out of his nurſery of grace heere, and tranſplanting them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Orchard of glory in heauen, there to flouriſh as Palmes for euermore.</p>
            <p>But had this her ſonne bin taken away in his infancy, her ſorrow had been the leſſe; ſhee had ſuſtained paine and ſorrow in bringing him into the word, care and feare in his nurture and education, and now that ſhee thought to haue receiued ſome comfort in him, for whom ſhee had often both wearied, and diſquieted her ſelfe; behold, he dyes.</p>
            <p>Thus it pleaſeth God many times to deale with his deareſt children, to lay af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction after affliction, putting into all their cups of comfort and contentments,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14554:9"/> bitter drams of ſorrow &amp; griefe. Whence wee may learne, firſt how vncertaine a thing it is to expect any certaine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in this world, we are all ſubiect to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſsitude, change and alteration. We muſt not expect any perpetuity of felicity here, leſt wee ſhould forget to looke after any other heauen then heere on earth. Doe not we ſee by experience, that kingdomes haue their declenſions, and Crownes and Scepters their croſſes? and ſhall priuate and particular perſons expect greater ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility? Secondly, it muſt teach vs how to entertaine comforts, when God ſendes them; euen as the Apoſtle bids vs the world, ſo to <hi>vſe them, as though wee vſed them not.</hi> So to reſolue of them, as if to morrow we were to take our leaues of them. As croſſes and afflictions are not of the nature of thoſe diſeaſes which men ſhall haue but once, and therefore wee are ſo to take our leaue of them to day, as to morrow to expect their returne: ſo on the other ſide thoſe comforts which men enioy in this world, are not perpetuall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidenſaries,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:14554:9"/> but euen like man himſelfe, of <hi>ſhort continuance,</hi> their <hi>dayes are but a ſpan</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſalm. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9. 6.</note> 
               <hi>long,</hi> they are alwayes <hi>in tranſitu,</hi> ſuddenly vaniſhed and gone, and therefore we muſt reſolue no otherwiſe on their company, then of paſſengers and trauailers, heere to day, and to morrow no more ſeene.</p>
            <p>Yea, but this was not all, it was not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the fruit of <hi>her</hi> body that was thus vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely cut off, but it was <hi>her</hi> onely ſonne; the holy ghoſt emphatically ad des, that ſhee was a <hi>widdow,</hi> and this was (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>her</hi> onely begotten ſonne, ſhee neuer had any other, <hi>Solum hunc in doloribus nouerat, ſolum ſuis lactauerat vberibus,</hi> neither had ſhe any hope of more, for <hi>her</hi> husband was dead, and this onely ſon left vnto <hi>her</hi> as a pledge and remembrance of <hi>her</hi> husbands loue; the ſight of whoſe louely face ſhe vſed (as <hi>Saul</hi> did <hi>Dauids</hi> muſicke) to driue away the vexing ſpirit of ſorrow and griefe: yea more, ſhe was not onely hereby deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of comfort, but altogether hopeleſſe of poſterity; for this <hi>her</hi> ſonne was <hi>baccu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus ſenectutis, ſtirps generis, ramuſculus ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionis,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:14554:10"/> and now the inheritance was left for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ng on to inherit. Was not heere cauſe of griefe? I might ſay, almoſt of deſpaire.</p>
            <p>T'is true; yet happily God did deale thus with her, euen becauſe it was <hi>her</hi> one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſonne, thereby to puniſh ſome ſinne in the mother; it may be ſhe had taken too much delight in this <hi>her</hi> ſonne and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God cauſed <hi>her</hi> to ſuſtaine much ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for him dead, whom happily liuing, ſhe did too much affect; <hi>her</hi> motherly care was turned into an ouer-prized indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence; now God makes that <hi>her</hi> greateſt croſſe, wherin ſhe expected greateſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort; becauſe ſhee made that <hi>her</hi> pride, which ſhould haue beene <hi>her</hi> care. The moſt louely flowers of hearts-delighting ioy, eftſoones proue the vntimely and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected ſeedes of bitter ſorrow, and God willing to weane our childiſh affections from that ouer-weening opinion we haue of earthly delights, many times ſo brings to paſſe, that in the fruition of what things our ioy hath abounded, in the loſſe of the ſame, our ſorrow ſhould much more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14554:10"/> But let not mee heere lay open a pit of deſpaire for any afflicted ſoule, nor adde ſinne to <hi>her</hi> ſorrow; the holy Ghoſt layes none to her charge, then why ſhould I? but rather ſay with our Sauiour, Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did this yong man ſinne, nor this wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, <hi>but that the workes of God might be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iohn 9. 3.</note> 
               <hi>in them,</hi> as hereafter wee ſhall heare. Only let this teach vs Chriſtian wiſdome, ſo to temper our affections in a godly me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diocrity, and ſo diſpoſe &amp; order our loue and delight in earthly things, that it neuer carry vs beyond Religion, beyond our ſelues, ſo ſhall we make the yoke of Gods afflictions eaſie vnto vs, ſo ſhall wee with a great deale of patience part with our greateſt and moſt endeared delights.</p>
            <p>Well, admit this was inflicted on <hi>her</hi> as a puniſhment for her ſinne, why was not ſhee ſtrooken with death her ſelfe, that as liuing ſhe could not expect many croſſes, ſo being dead, might neuer feele more ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row? No doubt, <hi>her</hi> loue was as great to this her only ſonne liuing, and her ſorrow for him dead, as euer was <hi>Dauids</hi> to <hi>Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:14554:11"/> when hee cryed, <hi>Oh my ſonne Abſolon,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 18. 33.</note> 
               <hi>my ſonne, my ſonne Abſolon, would God I had ayed for thee.</hi> Had it been in her owne ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, ſhee would haue redeemed <hi>her</hi> ſons life with the loſſe of <hi>her</hi> owne. But God deales many times with his children, as wife Tutors vnto Princes children, ſtrike them whom they moſt affect, and though hee doeth not correct them in his wrath and furie, yet he chooſeth ſo to ſmite, the ſmart may longeſt remaine.</p>
            <p>By this time I thinke you haue heard of a miſerable <hi>(Her)</hi> a diſtreſſed widdow, and you may wel ioyne with <hi>her,</hi> and ſhe with <hi>Eliah, It is enough, O Lord, take my ſoule.</hi> For <note place="margin">2 Kng. 19. 4.</note> it is not to bee doubted, but while <hi>her</hi> ſonne lay ſicke on his death bed, the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſate dayly on or by the bed, with ſad fighes, with feruent and deuout prayers, ſoliciting God, that now it was high time to put to his helping hand, and to bee mindful in the performance of thoſe moſt gracious promiſes that he had made vnto widdowes, that now it was ſeaſonable to make good that doctrine which the day
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14554:11"/> before he had deliuered in words, <hi>Bleſsed are they that mourne, for they ſhall be comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> but yet ſhe is not heard, <hi>her</hi> ſonne dies: By whoſe death ſhee was plunged into ſuch a depth of griefe, and almoſt ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed vp in a gulfe of deſpaire, that now ſhee could no longer conteine, but needes muſt breake foorth into open weeping, manifeſtly ſhewing thereby, that either the promiſes of God were vaine, and of none effect, or that ſhee was caſt off, and forſaken of God, and ſo his promiſes did in no wiſe appertaine vnto <hi>her:</hi> for theſe two (widdowhood, and want of iſſue) were accounted among the Iſraelites to be two great curſes. Yet more, <hi>her</hi> miſery was ſo great, that it moued all the Citie to commiſeration: for they went out with <hi>her</hi> vnto the graue, and now there was no hope of any effect of Gods promiſes, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching comfort to this mournefull wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow.</p>
            <p>VVhence we may learne, that God doth ſuffer his children many times to be ſo much cruſhed vnder the yoke of affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14554:12"/> and outward croſſes in this world, that not onely to the eye of men they ſeeme to be forſaken, but euen in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues they feele no comfort, find no hope. Thus was <hi>Dauid</hi> many times ſo heauily burdened, that hee ſeemed vnto himſelfe, as though hee were forſaken: <hi>Hath the Lord forgotten to be mercifull? hath he ſhut vp his mercies in displeaſure for euermore?</hi> So our bleſſed Sauiour himſelfe when hee was in the fleſh, felt the hand of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo heauy vpon him, that it made him in the bitterneſſe and anguiſh of his ſoule to cry out, <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forfaken me?</hi> This is the doing of the Lord, and it may ſeeme maruailous in our eyes, vntill we conſider the reaſons; which may be reduced to theſe three heads:</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe extremities are the beſt tryals of a Chriſtians faith: ordinary croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as they are common, ſo is it more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile to beare them. To hope well when we ſee no danger, or to beleeue Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, when we ſee them either alreadie performed, or at leaſt a probable and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:14554:12"/> meanes to effect them; it is eaſie, any man can doe it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but to hope when we ſee no hope of ſafetie, and to beleeue Gods faithfulneſſe, when wee ſee no other meanes, but as to rayſe children out of ſtones, to fetch water out of a flintie Rocke, to hold out a three yeeres famine with an handfull of meale, and a little oyle; here indeed is a true hope, and a noble tryall of a ſtrong faith: for hope that is ſeene is no hope, and faith groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on, or guided by the blind leader of carnall reaſon, is no faith. Thus God tryed <hi>Abrahams</hi> faith in that great extremitie, when he commanded him to offer vp his onely ſonne. Thus was <hi>Iobs</hi> faith, pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and conſtancie tryed by thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme croſſes on his bodie, goods, and children. God dealeth with his children, as Fencers with their ſcholers; they firſt begin with woodden cudgels, after they goe to weapons with blunted edges and points, and laſt of all, as they grow in skill, and to put their skill to the tryall, they play at ſharpe, and many times fetch
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:14554:13"/> blood. So God inures his children, firſt vnto pettie croſſes, and ſo inflicteth grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and greater, at laſt hee will ſtrike with the ſharpe, and draw blood from their ſoules, onely to try what proficients they haue beene in the ſchoole of faith and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience.</p>
            <p>Secondly, becauſe hee would make the deliuerance the more ioyfull, when it doth come: for the greater are our affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, the greater ſhall be the waight of glory, and the more welcome vnto vs: as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh concerning ſinne in the godly: ſo it is true concerning af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, God many times ſo bringing to paſſe, that where ſorrow hath abounded, there ioy ſhould much more abound: So that afflictions, they are but preparatiues to greater comforts.</p>
            <p>Vintners we ſee oftentimes ſet before their gueſts that haue dainty palates, bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh and ſalt meates, that ſo their wine may haue the better taſte and reliſh: So becauſe it is mans nature too ſlightly to eſteeme of the mercies, fauours, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14554:13"/> of God, as either to forget, or to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuate and leſſen them, hee doth many times giue them full cuppes of bitter ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, to the end that they may the more highly eſteeme and prize his mercies and fauours when he beſtowes them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, God ſeemes to leaue his with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all hope of comfort, becauſe they ſhould aſcribe all the praiſe and honour of their deliuerance vnto him onely. Man is of a dogged nature; as in aduerſitie, like the dogge that ſnarles and bites at the ſtone, and neuer lookes to the hand that threw it: ſo in proſperitie, when wee fare well, and obtaine any bleſſed and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table deliuerance from any euill, wee are readie preſently to ſhare glory with God, ſaying, This haue I gotten by my care, induſtrie, and wiſedome, or elſe attribute it vnto ſecond cauſes, and neuer looke vp vnto God to giue him the glorie. But let vs know, that God is a ielous God, he will not part ſtakes with any man; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he will many times ſuffer vs to ſinke ſo low, that all meanes in the world ſhall
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:14554:14"/> faile, before he will raiſe vs vp, to the end we may acknowledge, that God is aboue, and beyond all meanes.</p>
            <p>The vſe of this ſhall be none other then thoſe words of Saint <hi>Peter, Dearely belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 4. 12.</note> 
               <hi>thinke it not ſtrange concerning the fierie tryall which is among you, to prooue you, as though ſome ſtrange thing were come vnto you:</hi> but put on <hi>Iobs</hi> reſolution, <hi>Though the Lord</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iob 13. 15.</note> 
               <hi>ſlay me, yet will I put my truſt in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus haue you ſeene a tragicall ſcene of ſorrow, perſonated and acted in and by a miſerable and mournful widow, lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the loſſe of <hi>her</hi> onely ſonne: now we are come to make it end in a ioyfull <hi>plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite,</hi> while we looke vpon Chriſt <hi>her</hi> mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull comforter; for hee ſeeing <hi>her,</hi> hath <hi>compaſsion on her, and ſayth vnto her, VVeepe not.</hi> Wherein wee may obſerue theſe parts: 1. The time: <hi>When the Lord ſaw her:</hi> 2. The authour, <hi>The Lord:</hi> 3. Two ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent cauſes of of her comfort: firſt, Chriſt his omniſcience or prouidence, hee <hi>ſaw her;</hi> and this I may call the ſeed of her comfort: ſecondly, his mercy, <hi>he had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſsion</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:14554:14"/> 
               <hi>on her:</hi> and this I may call the ground, into which it was caſt, and where it tooke roote. 4. The comfort it ſelfe, which is firſt verball onely, <hi>Weepe not:</hi> and here it is ſprung into a blade: Secondly reall; for ſhe receiued her ſonne againe, as the Hiſtory ſheweth: and thus it is growne to an eare.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>When the Lord ſaw her.</hi> Was there a time when Chriſt did not know <hi>her</hi> miſerie? no: Chriſt knew before hee came to ſee <hi>her,</hi> and by his Almighty power, whiles her ſonne lay vpon his death-bed, could haue preuented his death, and his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſorrow, but he deferres it vntill this time; to teach vs this leſſon; That God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone beſt knowes when to wound, and when to heale; when to kill, and when to make aliue, when to afflict with ſorrow, and when to ſend comfort: we are not to limit God to times and ſeaſons, nor yet to preſcribe vnto him when wee ſhould haue deliuerances from dangers, and comfort in croſſes and afflictions. <hi>My times</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid)</hi> that is, times of proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:14554:15"/> and aduerſity, <hi>are in thy hand:</hi> that is, to order and diſpoſe according to thy wiſedome, to thy good will and pleaſure. And therefore though the Lord may ſeem a long time not to giue audience, nor yet to behold the afflictions of his Saints; yet there wil come a <hi>when,</hi> a time, that will bring comfort vnto them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Lord:</hi> Heere is the Author. All true &amp; ſound comfort comes from God in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and from him onely is to bee expected; hee is the Father of mercies, and God of all comfort: it is hee that ſendes comfort in afflictions, yea life in death it ſelfe, by his power and mercy hee ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens the bitter waters of death, with the wood of his Croſſe, making that which is ſeene, as <hi>though it</hi> were not: ſo that though he hath not taken away death it ſelfe, yet he hath taken away the tyrannicall pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of death, inſomuch that through him wee may inſultingly ſay, <hi>Oh death where is thy ſting.</hi> Chriſt is the true hearbe of grace, which doth mitigate (if not wonderfully ſweeten) all thoſe cups of gall and vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:14554:15"/> which are the <hi>portion</hi> and the <hi>potion,</hi> of the children of grace here, before they can be the children of glory in heauen.</p>
            <p>The Vſe whereof is, firſt, to ſtirre vp euery one of vs, to ſeeke onely vnto God for comfort, and to ſatiate and delight our ſelues onely in him, as in the God of all comfort and conſolation: If hee ſend vs comfort, if he be the rocke vpon whom wee build our conſolation, no affliction can diſcomfort vs, no feare can afright vs, nor death it ſelfe can diſmay or appall vs; vnto him therefore, and onely to him, let vs ſeeke for comfort.</p>
            <p>Secondly, heereby is diſcouered and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooued, the vngodly practiſe amongſt many now adayes, that in the time of ſorrow in ſtead of going to God for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, they runne a cleane contrary way to the deuill. They will goe to an Ale houſe to drinke away ſorrow, or elſe get them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues into ſome jouiall company, and to paſſe away the time. And ſo likewiſe, in the time of ſickeneſſe, in ſtead of looking vp to heauen, they take hell for comfort;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:14554:16"/> by ſeeking to beguile the time, and paſſe away the tediouſneſſe of the paine, with idle tales, cardes, dice, or ſome ſuch like vanitie.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it yeeldes matter of comfort vnto Gods children, when they ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that God is their comforter, what need they feare, who bee their tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor? If wee had the keeping of this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in our owne hands and hearts onely, as <hi>Adam</hi> had his innocency, wee might eaſily leeſe it as <hi>Adam</hi> did his, and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan</hi> who was euer enuious of mans good, would be ready to picke and ſteale it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from vs; but God keepes it for vs in heauen, and as hee did vnto the children of Iſrael in the wilderneſſe, daily renew ſhowres of <hi>Manna,</hi> ſo doth he diſtill drops of heauenly comfort daily, into the hearts of true Iſraelites, in this their wilderneſſe, and vale of teares.</p>
            <p>Thus of the Author, now of the Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: The firſt antecedent cauſe, or the ſeed of the womans comfort was, that <hi>the Lord ſaw her.</hi> As not ſhee, no more can any
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:14554:16"/> Saint of God bee in any diſtreſſe, but hee ſees it, and good reaſon; <hi>for he that made the eye, ſhall not he ſee? He that made the eare, ſhall not he heare? and hee that made the heart, ſhall not he vnderſtand</hi> the ſorrowes of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry afflicted ſoule? Yes, he ſees, he heares, he vnderſtands all. Neither comfort, nor bleſſing, croſſe, nor curſe can come vnto vs, but by Gods prouidence and fore-ſight: not a haire of our heades can be diminiſhed, nor a cubite can be added vnto our ſtature, without the prouidence of our heauenly Father. It is neither con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtellation of ſtarres, influence of the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall bodyes, coniunctions of Planets, nor any ſuch notionall fantaſie of a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematicall braine, that can worke our weale or woe. It is not the malice of the deuill, or wicked men, can hurt Gods Church, or children; for God ſees, his prouidence is aboue all. And this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence of God, hath as well a reſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as ordaining power: for if either ſtrength, or policie, could preuaile againſt Gods Church it could not ſtand, if either
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:14554:17"/> the curſes of men, or the indeauours of the powers of darkneſſe ſhould bee effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall, all would bee hell: but God ſees, and his prouidence diſpoſeth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Lord ſaw her;</hi> Hee did not ſhut his eyes, nor turne his backe vpon <hi>her,</hi> but <hi>ſees her,</hi> takes eſpeciall notice of <hi>her;</hi> to teach man what hee ſhould doe, to turne his eyes from beholding vanitie, &amp; looke vpon the poore ſaints of God in miſerie. What's the reaſon men ſhould now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes, ſo much degenerate fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Chriſt</hi> their Lord? Men now adayes are growen like the Oſtrich, that while her egges are in the ſand, ſhee will not looke on them; ſhee leaues them, ſhe forgets them. When the clouds of aduerſitie ariſe, mens ſights are dimmed, they cannot ſee: when <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> is in aduerſitie, <hi>his friends and his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance ſtand afarre off;</hi> What's the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon? Surely, men either haue their eyes, through ſelfe-loue turned inward, onely to looke vpon themſelues; or els the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits and pleaſures of this world, play the <hi>Philistims</hi> with <hi>Sampſon,</hi> cleane put out
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:14554:17"/> their eyes, and ſo they are become idoles; eyes they haue, and ſee not the miſeries of Gods ſaints. Let ſuch take heed, leaſt <hi>the Lord giue them alſo a ſorrowfull mind, and a trembling heart, and they looke for comfort in vaine, till their eyes fall out. Deut. 28. 61. For hee that hideth his eyes from the poore, ſhall haue many curſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Lord ſaw her:</hi> Marke the gradation which heere the holy Ghoſt vſeth, it is worth the noting, hee ſpake comfort vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this woman, <hi>VVeepe not.</hi> But firſt, <hi>hee had compaſsion on her,</hi> and before hee had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſion on <hi>her,</hi> he <hi>ſaw her;</hi> not that any thing in God is firſt or laſt, for all things with him are coeternall, and admit no prioritie of ſubſiſtence, but onely as hee doth actuate them towards men. Firſt, <hi>hee ſees,</hi> then hee <hi>is mooued with compaſsion,</hi> then he ſpeakes comfort, <hi>VVeepe not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To ſhew vs that God may <hi>ſee,</hi> though hee haue not <hi>compaſsion,</hi> hee may haue <hi>compaſsion</hi> though hee doe not preſently comfort; if hee comfort not, yet hee may haue <hi>compaſsion;</hi> and though he ſhew not
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:14554:18"/> 
               <hi>compaſsion,</hi> yet certainely hee <hi>ſees:</hi> which may ſerue for admirable comfort to Gods children, when the ſwelling waters of ſorrow are cleane gone ouer their ſoules; though the Lord doth not preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſend thee comfort, yet hee may haue <hi>compaſsion</hi> on thee; and though as yet hee hath not <hi>compaſsion,</hi> yet certainely he <hi>ſees:</hi> and ſeeing thee is a cauſe to mooue him to <hi>compaſsion,</hi> and his <hi>compaſsion</hi> will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely in the ende bring comfort. The like gradation God vſeth in his iuſtice, towards ſinners, which may be a terrour to euery impenitent perſon; firſt he ſeeth their ſinnes, then his wrath is kindled, and his <hi>iealouſie waxeth hot,</hi> and then hee ſtrikes, and therefore though hee doeth not plague a ſinner preſently, yet hee is angry, and though hee ſeeme not to bee angrie, yet certainely hee ſees him, and the ſight of his ſinnes will kindle his wrath: and <hi>who knowes the power of his wrath?</hi> ſurely it will being a fearefull iudgement.</p>
            <p>Secondly, God doth firſt <hi>ſee</hi> our miſery,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:14554:18"/> before hee is moued with <hi>compaſsion,</hi> and ſend comfort? let it teach euery Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an that deſires comfort; firſt of all to make his miſery knowen vnto God. We are all beggers, and they we know vſe to lay open their vlcers and ſores, to mooue the paſſengers <hi>compaſsion.</hi> Let vs not bee ſo proud as to ſcorne to lay open our wants vnto God, for except God <hi>ſee</hi> our miſery, how can hee haue <hi>compaſsion?</hi> to conceale thy miſery from God, is to ſtop the fountaine &amp; well-head of Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. The Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> proues the truth hereof vnto vs, <hi>When I held my tongue,</hi> that is, while I concealed my miſery, and did not make it knowen vnto God, <hi>my bones conſumed:</hi> that is, my ſorrow increaſed, I found no comfort, <hi>then I acknowledged my ſinne vnto thee, neither hid I mine iniquity, for I thought, I will confeſſe againſt my ſelfe my wickedneſſe vnto the Lord, and thou forgaueſt the puniſhment of my ſinne.</hi> Vpon his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion God <hi>ſaw</hi> his miſery; <hi>ſeeing</hi> it, was moued with <hi>compaſsion;</hi> and this brought comfort. It was his practiſe: for <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:14554:19"/> before, in the 12, verſe he prayes, <hi>Reſtore vnto me the ioy of thy ſaluation.</hi> In the 5. <hi>verſ.</hi> he firſt inuites God to <hi>ſee</hi> and looke vpon <hi>his</hi> miſery, <hi>Behold, I was borne in iniquity, and in ſinne hath my mother conceiued me.</hi> God grant the like practiſe may be ours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Lord ſaw her.</hi> God hath a foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold eye: Firſt of Maieſty, Secondly of Iuſtice, Thirdly, of Prudence, Fourthly, of Compaſsion. With the firſt he lookes on himſelfe only, and this no man can ſee and liue, as God told <hi>Moyſes.</hi> With the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond hee lookes vpon ſinne and ſinners, and this is an eye of terror, it ſparkles with fire of reuenge, in regard whereof, euery man hath cauſe to pray, <hi>Turne thy face a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from our ſinnes.</hi> With the third, hee lookes on all his workes, and by it hee or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth all things in weight and meaſure. With the fourth, he lookes on the father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and widdowes, and all his poore and needie Saints: for ſeeing them, hee hath compaſſion on them, and they like the Sunne in the Firmament giues both life and light to all ſublunary bodies, by this
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:14554:19"/> is euery afflicted ſoule abundantly reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and inuited with boldneſſe to come vnto the Throne of grace, and cry <hi>Abba, Father.</hi> And for this may euery ſinner ſafely pray, Lord ſhew vs the light of thy countenance. Graciouſly looke vpon our afflictions, Pitifully behold the ſorrowes of our hearts. And with this eye did hee looke on this widdow: for ſeeing her, <hi>he had compaſsion on her.</hi> Heere is the ſecond antecedent cauſe of this womans com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fort, and may be called <hi>cauſa ſubalternata,</hi> as Logicians terme it, becauſe it is both an effect, and a cauſe, an effect, in reſpect it proceeded from Chriſt his ſeeing her; and a cauſe, in that it produced and effected her comfort. Firſt let vs conſider it an effect: Chriſt did not <hi>ſee her</hi> in miſery and paſſe by her without any regard, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> puts on the bowels of <hi>compaſsion,</hi> and is touched with the ſence of her ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, <hi>when he ſaw, he had compaſſion on her.</hi> The Prieſt may ſee the wounded man, and paſſe by on the one ſide, the Leuite may come neere the place, goe and looke
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:14554:20"/> on him, and paſſe by on the other ſide, but the good Samaritane Chriſt Ieſus, <hi>when he ſees</hi> him, <hi>he hath compaſſion</hi> on him.</p>
            <p>The vſe hereof is for exhortation, with thoſe words of the Apoſtle, <hi>Let the ſame minde bee in you that was euen in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> If wee are Chriſtians, let vs imitate our Maſter Chriſt Ieſus. <hi>Hee ſaw her,</hi> but what manner of ſight was this? There is a good ſight, and a bad ſight. The good ſight is threefold, Firſt, of diſcretion or diſcerning. Second, of contemplation. The third, of commiſeration; the laſt is the beſt, eſpecially when it hath the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Gods Saints for i'ts obiect: and the brighter our eyes are thus to ſee, the neerer wee come to God the Father, who is the God of mercy; and to God the Sonne, our Lord and Maſter, who neuer ſees his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants in miſery, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>hath compaſsion on them,</hi> and to God the holy Ghoſt, who is the <hi>comforter.</hi> But men now a dayes are quicke ſighted, but ſlow to haue <hi>compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi> They ſee as <hi>Cham</hi> to deride, as <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal</hi> to mocke, as <hi>Iobs</hi> friends, to eſpie out
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:14554:20"/> their ſinnes, to aggrauate their infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, to adde to their ſorrow, to trample vnder their feete the comfortleſſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected ſoule, in ſtead of powring wine and oyle into their wounds like Chriſt, like his tormentours giue <hi>gall and vineger to drinke.</hi> Is this Chriſtianiſme? t's contrary to the practiſe of Chriſt. Is it Religion? no; for <hi>pure Religion before God the Father, is to viſit the fatherleſſe and widdowes in their aduerſity.</hi> Surely then we may conclude, that more beare the name, then haue na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from Chriſt; more profeſſe, then pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe Religion; otherwiſe how can vvee behold the miſery<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of Gods Church and children vvithout compaſſionate, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenting hearts? How can we ſee the affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of <hi>Ioſeph, and yet drinke wine in bowles, and ſing to the ſound of the viall?</hi> How can wee ſee thoſe <hi>Foxes which deſtroy the vineyard,</hi> and not be moued with compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to pray vnto our Spouſe <hi>to take them?</hi> How can wee ſee that man of perdition <hi>Sampſon</hi>-like ſend Foxes with firebrands in their tayles into the Lords corne, and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:14554:21"/> not be moued with <hi>compaſsion</hi> to <hi>pray vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord of the harueſt?</hi> How can we ſee in our neighbouring countreyes abroad, the beauty of <hi>Sion</hi> to bee defaced, and her walles beaten downe almoſt euen with the ground, and not be moued with <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſsion, nor haue any pity on the duſt thereof?</hi> Let vs beware leſt the like happen vnto vs, and there bee none to pity, nor to haue compaſſion on vs. How can we at home ſee ſo many poore, needy, naked, ſicke, and comfortleſſe Chriſtians lie in miſery and want, and we paſſe by like ſo many Prieſts and Leuites vvithout any remorſe, any <hi>compaſsion? Bleſſed are the mercifull, for they ſhall obtaine mercy:</hi> mercy and compaſſion it is one badge of a true Chriſtian heere on earth, <hi>by this ſhall men know that you are my diſciples, if yee loue one another.</hi> It is the only Brand-mark that I read of, by which Chriſt at the laſt day ſhal know the ſheep from the goats, <hi>Come yee bleſſed of my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for I was hungrie and yee fed mee, naked, and yee clothed mee, in priſon and yee viſited mee.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:14554:21"/>
            <p>
               <hi>He had compaſsion on her:</hi> Now conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it, as it was a cauſe of her comfort, or as the ground whereinto the ſeed of her comfort was caſt and tooke root. Chriſt was not ſent vnto, to come to rayſe her dead ſonne, and being come, was not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated or ſued vnto, but voluntarily, and out of his owne accord; for hee was mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with <hi>compaſsion,</hi> t'was his mercy and <hi>compaſsion</hi> that was the cauſe of her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort. To teach vs, firſt, that what bleſſing or comfort ſoeuer either ſpirituall or tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall we enioy, Gods mercy is the cauſe of it. It muſt bee his mercy alone, that muſt feoffe vs in all bleſſings and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts whatſoeuer, and except this mercy of God in Chriſt, feoffe vs in bleſſings and comforts, as our ſins do in croſſes &amp; cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes wee periſh. Secondly, that God of himſelfe is ſo ready to haue mercy that <hi>before we call be will anſwere; and whiles wee ſpeake, he will heare:</hi> he loues not onely to exceed our ſinnes, but our very deſires in mercy. Thirdly, we may ſee the gradation of Chriſt his loue to his ſaints, deſcending
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:14554:22"/> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them by a ladder fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen, by three ſteppes or rounds: <hi rend="sup">1</hi> in heart, <hi rend="sup">2</hi> in word, <hi rend="sup">3</hi> in deed: in heart, for <hi>he hath compaſsion:</hi> in word, with a <hi>noli flere, weepe not:</hi> in deed, for hee reſtored her dead ſonne to life, but firſt it beginnes at the heart. Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers teach vs, that life naturall firſt begins at the heart; ſo grace, the life ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, is firſt feated in the ſoule; the heart is firſt mooued to <hi>compaſsion,</hi> then the toung to pitie: for <hi>(ex abundantia cordis) out of the aboundance of the heart, the tongue ſpeaketh;</hi> and hee that hath not a compaſſionate heart, cannot haue a pitifull tongue, but from the teeth outward, and not to ſpeake comfortably, or ſhew comfort, by word or deed, or both, is an euident ſigne of a hard heart; and from hardneſſe of heart good Lord deliuer vs.</p>
            <p>You haue heard the cauſes of her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, Chriſt his <hi>ſeeing</hi> her, &amp; Chriſts <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſsion on her,</hi> now heare the effect of both, <hi>he ſaith vnto her, VVeepe not. Hee ſaw her:</hi> here the comfort was but in the ſeed. <hi>Hee had compaſsion:</hi> there the ſeed was caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:14554:22"/> the ground, and tooke deepe roote. <hi>VVeepe not:</hi> here it is ſprung into a blade. This good Samaritan Chriſt Ieſus, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenteth not himſelfe to ſee this wounded woman, (for indeed ſhe had a <hi>wounded ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit)</hi> and to haue <hi>compaſsion on her,</hi> but goes vnto her, bindes vp her wounds, poures wine and oyle into them, and takes care for her farther comfort, <hi>weepe not.</hi> To teach vs, that it is not ſufficient for vs, when we ſee any in miſerie, onely to bee moued with compaſſion, but wee muſt ſpeake ſome <hi>words of comfort in due ſeaſon:</hi> it is the Apoſtle his rule, our tongues muſt vtter the tender affections of our hearts; and our hearts, as they are, or ſhould bee the ground, where mercy muſt roote, muſt ſometimes ſhew, that there is life, by ſending fourth ſome buddes into the tongue, which is the hearts beſt interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and commonly ſpeakes the language of the heart; if the heart conceiue <hi>compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> the tongue muſt vtter <hi>weepe not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVeepe not.</hi> Here comes our Sauiour now, and makes good in performance his
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:14554:23"/> comfortable doctrine, which was in words and promiſes; <hi>Bleſsed are they that mourne:</hi> hee comes with a towell in his hands, and wipes away the briniſh teares from the blubbered and furrowed cheeks of this ſorrowfull widow, and turnes her ſadneſſe into gladneſſe, her faſting in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to feaſting; her ſobbes and ſighes, into ſongs and prayſes of deliuerance: ſuch is the power, prouidence, and mercy of our gracious Lord, and mercifull Sauiour, to rayſe vp vnto his children in the middeſt of ſorrow, ſudden and vnexpected com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</p>
            <p>But here ſome ſad deiected Chriſtian, co-partner with this widow in the ſame or like cauſe of griefe, may yet refuſe to be comforted, and iuſtifie both the cauſe and act of ſorrow: for the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> complained in his dayes, that <hi>the righteous man periſhed, and no man conſidered it in his heart:</hi> beſides, it is not found through the whole ſacred Storie of our Sauiours life, that euer hee was ſeene to laugh, but to weepe often: and beſides all, this woman
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:14554:23"/> loſt her ſonne, and therefore a ſenſleſſe ſtupiditie in her, not to haue mourned, would haue argued not onely want of loue, but of nature and humanitie, or to haue had <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, courage aboue and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the ſtrength of nature: for how qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et ſoeuer the morall Doctors haue made themſelues, yet their rules haue neuer counteruailed all their troubles. The wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt and moſt reſolute Moraliſt that euer was, look't pale, when he was to taſte his poyſonfull Hemlocke, and why? becauſe to grieue at croſſes, and to feare death is naturall, is to bee a man; why then doth our Sauiour forbid her, ſaying; <hi>VVeepe not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We muſt know for all this, that the God of nature will haue vs ſometime, (though not to deny) yet to curbe nature; and grace muſt teach vs to doe that ſometime which nature cannot, for courage and conſtancie againſt all croſſes, and then to be leaſt ſhaken, when moſt aſſayled, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth from the rules of an higher art then naturall wiſedome was euer able to teach. Not that grace would make a man not be
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:14554:24"/> affectionate, as not to mourne with them that mourne, and <hi>weep with them that weepe:</hi> for euen this is a leſſon which euery man muſt learne in the ſchoole of grace; but di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect vs to moderate the inordinate, and ouer-paſſionate affections of nature, that they ſhould not <hi>meurne as men without hope, for them that ſleepe in the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Weepe not.</hi> Here (mee thinkes) I am ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with admiration, to conceiue in what amazement this ſorrowfull ſoule, and all the mournfull company ſtood, to ſee one ſilly man, and that a ſtranger, to come with ſuch a ſong of melody into a <hi>houſe of mourning,</hi> and to preſent ſuch a diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and diſcording dittie to ſo dolefull a tune, and yet I cannot chuſe but admire more, how ſuddenly their ſorrow was tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into comfort, and mourning into mirth; while I conſider, who it is that ſayes vnto her, <hi>weepe not. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ox hominem ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat, oh Deus certè,</hi> the ſound of the voyce bewrayes him to be a man, but the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that he ſpeakes, <hi>mightily declares him to be the Sonne of God.</hi> God ſpeakes by his
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:14554:24"/> Sonne, the brightneſſe of his glory, and the engraued forme of his Perſon, out of his Word vnto all, both good and bad: but it is not the ſound of the voyce of God, but the matter which he ſpeaks, that argues loue: he may ſpeake vnto an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie as vnto Satan, <hi>Satan whence commeſt thou? Iob</hi> 1. in anger, as vnto <hi>Adam,</hi> when he called him to an account, <hi>Adam where art tbou? Gen.</hi> 3. He ſpeakes peace to none but to his owne: it is vnto them and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their ſoules that he ſayes, <hi>I am thy ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> It is with them that hee doth indent, <hi>I will be their God, and they ſhall be my people:</hi> and happy that ſoule vnto whom in the middeſt of ſorrow, Chriſt ſhall vtter this comfortable voyce, <hi>Weepe not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Church of God is compared to a ſhip ſayling on the ſea; euery Chriſtian is a paſſenger in this Veſſell, Chriſt is the Pilot and Steeres-man, he ſtill ſits at the Helme, let the weather be neuer ſo foule, let the ſea and waues of croſſes riſe one vpon another with neuer ſuch ſwelling ſurges, yet if my Sauiour ſay vnto my
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:14554:25"/> ſoule, <hi>I am thy ſaluation,</hi> I will neuer deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire, if my ſteeres-man ſay vnto mee as vnto his Diſciples, <hi>Feare not, O yee of litle faith,</hi> that little faith I haue ſhall make me ſo confident as not to be diſmayed, if my Sauiour meete mee, though not in the fleſh, yet but in his word, as he doth here this comfortleſſe widow with a <hi>noli flere, weepe not,</hi> though he take away from mee father or mother, brother or ſiſter, my neareſt and deareſt comfort in the world, I will not mourne as without hope, but comfort my ſelfe in his comfortable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes.</p>
            <p>Thus haue you ſeene a ſorrowfull mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, following <hi>her</hi> dead ſonne with teare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dewed cheekes, a paſſionate multitude at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending this penſiue widow, a compaſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Lord ſtopping their mouthes, wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping their eyes, and cheering their hearts, with a comfortable <hi>noli flere, VVeepe not.</hi> But this is not all, let me adde ſomething farther then my Text, yet not beyond the Text, for t'is in the Hyſtory hee gaue <hi>her her</hi> ſonne aliue againe; and thus the blade
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:14554:25"/> is growne to an eare, from a verball to a reall comfort. To teach vs firſt, that it is not ſufficient for vs to haue a tender heart and a bemoaning tongue, to thoſe that are in want and miſerie, but our handes muſt be inlarged, our hearts towards poor needy Chriſtians muſt be ſo affected, that ſome worke of charitie and mercy, might be effected.</p>
            <p>Secondly, and for concluſion of all, whereas this woman in the depth of <hi>her</hi> ſorrow found comfort, and the yong man in the midſt of death found life, we may learne, that both to liue, and to liue comfortably, are in, and from <hi>Christ</hi> alone.</p>
            <p>But ſome ſorrowfull ſoule may yet farther obiect and reaſon, that well might this woman receiue a great deale of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, for ſhee had the reall and bodily pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of <hi>her</hi> bleſſed Sauiour, whoſe very lookes were able to reuiue a drooping and languiſhing ſoule; and beſides to his preſence, he annexed his Power, miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly raiſing her dead ſonne to life, and thereby vnexpected comfort to her ſelfe,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:14554:26"/> but now <hi>Chriſt</hi> is aſcended into heauen, and there ſhall remaine till his ſecond comming; beſides miracles are now cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, how then ſhall I by this example any whit comfort my ſelfe; how ſhall I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect reſtitution of my loſſe, reſtauration of my comfort.</p>
            <p>I anſwere, theſe doubts proceed but from the weakneſſe of our faith; ſhall the eyes of the body miniſter comfort to the ſoule, and ſhall not Faith the Eye of the ſoule doe much more? Rubbe but the ſcales of infidelitie from theſe eyes; and then, euen now by faith thou mayeſt ſee thy Sauiour, ſitting at the right hand of God, making continuall interceſſion for thee. But why doe I grant that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is abſent from his Church and children? Hee is not; as <hi>Abraham</hi> in the Parable anſwered <hi>Diues, They haue Moſes and the Prophets,</hi> ſo I ſay, wee haue <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſtill; haue we not his owne promiſe: <hi>Loe, I am with you to the end of the world.</hi> Doth hee not daily ſpeake vnto our ſoules, by the Spirit, the Comforter, and to our eares by his holy word, as comfortably as euer
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:14554:26"/> hee did vnto this woman, when hee ſayd vnto her, <hi>VVeepe not.</hi> May not wee daily heare him ſay; <hi>Bleſſed are the poore in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; Bleſsed are they that mourne for they ſhall bee comforted; Come vnto mee all yee that are heauy laden, and I will refreſh you, and you ſhall finde reſt vnto your ſoules.</hi> As for the comfort this woman had, by the rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of <hi>her</hi> dead ſonne, know, that this was but a temporall and ſhort life, and when hee badde <hi>her</hi> not to weepe, this comfort was as ſhort, if not ſhorter then the former; for certainely afterwards ſo long as ſhee liued, ſhee would haue cauſe to weepe, by daily renewed cauſes of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row. But wee howſoeuer wee looſe our friends now, ſhall one day ſee a more bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed raiſing of them, neuer any more to bee depriued of their ſocietie: and then ſhall <hi>Chriſt</hi> pronounce words which ſhall bring more durable comfort then theſe to this woman, for then ſhall <hi>all teares bee wiped from our eyes neuer</hi> to feele more ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row. Till which time the Lord giue vs grace to liue religiouſly, and to wait patiently.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
